This is Arpan Kumar, who
worked at American Express, Gurgaon. On July 5, 2019,
he was on his way to work and met with an accident. The
accident was so severe that he suffered a
significant brain injury. After which, he was
admitted to Mittal Hospital. His
condition was quite severe, and his health
gradually began to improve.
We know that it was a brain injury, so
recovery took a long time. As he
gradually stabilized, he was
suggested to join a rehabilitation center.
However, the issue was that the treatment there was
quite expensive. Arpan belongs to a middle-
class family, and
he never imagined that this day would come.
But now that it came, his family
claimed health insurance through the company where Arpan worked,
which was worth Rs 5 lakh. However, his initial
treatment alone cost Rs 80,000,
which exhausted all his personal savings.
Due to just one accident,
all the savings of his family were lost,
but by taking a proper health insurance, he could have
avoided all this and you must have also
understood that the
health insurance provided by the company is
not sufficient, so if you also love your family
and do not want that you or
your family should not face such a situation, then
you should take a good health insurance as soon as possible,
but the issue is that there are many
companies and they provide many types of health
insurance, so
which health insurance is the best among them, in today's
video I will tell you which
health insurance is the best and what exactly you should look for
while selecting health insurance,
from where to buy this insurance
and if you ever need to make a claim, then
from where can you make a claim,
so let us know
what factors you have to keep in mind while taking health insurance so
that you are not cheated, so the
first question that comes to mind is
how much health insurance should I take, 5 lakh, 10 lakh
or 15 lakh, so according to me the ideal
You should take health insurance of two times your annual income,
for example, if
your annual income is 10 lakhs, then you should at least
take health insurance of up to 20 lakhs, but let me make it clear here
that even if your annual income is very low
or you are barely able to make ends meet, you
must still take insurance of at least 5 lakhs,
because there is no benefit in taking less than that. The
second factor is the room
rent type, for example, you
took insurance of 20 lakhs, but the daily room
rent limit there is ₹ 10, so of course, you have
taken insurance of 20 lakhs, but the limit there
is 5000, so if you take a room above that, then
you will have to pay from your pocket, so
ideally it is believed that
we should take such health insurance in
which there is no limit on room rent, so the
third factor which comes in the health policy is
what benefits should be there,
so we should take such health insurance in
which pre-hospitalization
expenses are covered, so let us understand
this one.  For example, if there is an X-
ray person who has come to the hospital for cancer treatment,
then it means that
he has already incurred a lot of expenses
in diagnosis and reports. So, we should take the health
insurance which covers pre-hospitalization
expenses. Now
suppose someone has to undergo an operation and that
operation is done, then will
his expenses end immediately after the operation? No, obviously,
he will have to spend money even after that,
in medicine and OPD. So, post-hospitalization
expenses should also be covered in your health insurance.
We should also know
that health insurance mainly works only
when we are admitted in the hospital.
But suppose if we get a surgery done
which takes only 2 hours, then this should also be
included and this is called day care
expenses. So, it is also important that a good
health insurance has the option of day care. The
next factor which we have to remember is
copay. For example, your hospital
bill comes for Rs 5 lakh and your insurance
was for Rs 10 lakh and the company should pay the entire Rs 5 lakh.
If the copay in our agreement
is 20, then the company will only pay 4 lakhs and
you will have to pay 1 lakh. So,
whenever you choose health insurance,
check if there is any copay option. Now, the
next thing to look at is the claim paid
within three months. To see
how many insurances the company has passed
in the last three months, we should target a
passing date of 99 because the
higher the passing rate, the better. The
next thing to check is the
cashless hospitalization list. You need to check
which hospitals in your city
provide cashless services.
Mainly, all the big hospital
brands should be included. We need to
check this. Now, the most
important thing, which you will
not easily find out from anywhere, is that it is most important for you to
know what is not
covered in the insurance you are taking
because there is no policy
that covers everything. So, we always have to
check the exclusions in the policy document.  Does
it not cover it? Now you must have understood
how to buy health insurance,
but you
also need to know some important points here.
After that, I will tell you how you can do it if
you ever need to claim your health insurance. So
listen carefully. First, if you are young, the
sooner you take health insurance,
the less premium you will have to pay.
Second, if you take health insurance,
you will also get tax benefits.
Claim that too. Third, never
depend on the company's health insurance
because it is hardly worth Rs 5 lakh.
Like we saw in Arpan's case, the
health insurance was only worth Rs 5 lakh and
all the personal savings of the family were exhausted.
So let us know how you will make a claim.
Suppose you have to make a claim in an emergency,
like if there is
a case related to an accident, then as soon as this
incident happens, you should
inform the company within 24 hours. And if
your plan is hospitalization, then you can inform the
company 48 hours in advance on their toll free
number.  You can register otherwise there is
an insurance tax in every hospital,
you can go there and take help,
they will help you in getting it done,
so now you must have understood
how to take health insurance, what things to keep in
mind and along with this
how to make a claim, if you liked the video then do like it
and stay tuned for the next
update, thank you so much.